A Guide to the Virginia Health Services Cost Review Council, Records, 1978-1984
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Health Services Cost Review Council, Records, 1978-1984
Library of Virginia
33033
5 cubic feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Restricted
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Virginia Health Services Cost Review Council.
Historical Information
The rising cost of health care and the lack of comparative information on health care services was a concern of the legislature in 1971. A joint resolution was passed calling for special studies of the costs and Administration of Health Care Services, led by Senator Edward E. Willey. The commission recommended establishing a rate review board to "examine hospital costs and charges." In 1975, the Virginia Rate Review Program was set up as a separate not-for-profit corporation; this was formalized into a board the following year.
The Virginia Health Services Cost Review Council was created by an act of the General Assembly approved April 9, 1978. Initially, the Council was a Commission made up of nine members, eight of whom were appointed by the governor for a three year term: three consumers of health care services, three administrators of nongovernmental health care institutions, one employee of a prepaid hospital service plan, and one employee of a commercial insurer which underwrites accident and sickness insurance. The ninth member was the Commissioner of Health or his designee. The chairman was elected from the consumer members.
On April 4, 1980, the General Assembly approved enlarging the Commission to eleven members, increasing the consumer representatives to five, two with experience in financial management or accounting. The Commission became a Council effective July 1, 1982. The Director of the agency was hired by the Council members, reporting to the Secretary of Health and Human Services. The stated mission is to "promote the economic delivery of high quality and effective institutional health care services to the citizens of the Commonwealth." In 1989, the General Assembly expanded the Council's review of costs and charges to the long-term care industry, absorbing the Long-Term Care Council which was established in 1982.
The size of the council was increased to fifteen, in order to include three nursing home providers and the Director of the Department of Medical Assistant Services, and the executive director position became a gubernatorial appointment. The Council established a uniform system of financial reporting of health care costs. Each health care institution is required to file an annual financial report with details on health care costs, charges, assets, liabilities, and net worth. Through monthly meetings, the Council engages in continuing financial analysis and studies relating to health care institutions. The information gathered is disseminated to the public through its publications.
The Council may initiate reviews or investigations as necessary to assure all users of health care services that aggregate charges are reasonably aggregate costs, and that charges are equitable.
The major publications issued by the Virginia Health Services Cost Review Council include: Annual Report of Health Care Costs, "Charge Survey," and Commercial Diversification Report.
Scope and Content
This collection gives minutes, correspondence, subject files and support documentation highlighting the Commonwealth's effort to monitor and review the policies and budgetary procedures of hospitals and medical facilities within the state.
Arrangement
Organized into two (2) series: Series I. Minutes and Related Meeting Records, 1983-1984; Series II. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1978-1983.
Contents List
- Minutes and Related Meeting Records, 1983-1984
  - 27, July 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 24, August 1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 28, Septemeber 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 26, October 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 30, November 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 21, December 1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 25, January 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 22, February 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 24, March 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 25, April 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 23, May 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 27, June 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 26, September 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 28, November 1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence and Subject Files, 1978-1983
  - Alexandria Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Allegheny Regional Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Arlington Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bath County Community Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bedford County Memorial Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Blue Ridge Hospital, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Buchanan Hospital, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Colonial Institute for Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Cumberland (A Hospital for Children and Adolescents), 1983 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Charter Westbrook Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Chesapeake General Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Children's Hospital of the King's Daughter, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Children's Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Chippenham Hospital Inc., 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Chippenham Hospital Inc., 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Circle Terrace Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Commonwealth Doctor's Office, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Community Hospital of Roanoke Valley, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Community Memorial Hospital 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - David C. Wilson Neuro Psychiatric Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - DePaul Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Dominion Psychiatric Treatment Center, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Ear, Nose and Throat Hospital Inc., 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Fairfax Hospital Association, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Fairfax Surgery Center, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Fauquier Hospital Inc., 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Franklin Memorial Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Giles Memorial Hospital Inc., 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Gill Memorial Eye, Ear, Nose and Throat Hospital Inc., 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Graydon Manor (Formerly National Children's Rehab Hospital), 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Greensville Memorial Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Grundy Hospital Inc., 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Halifax Community Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Hampton General Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Henrico Doctor's Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Humana Hospital-Bayside, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Humana Hospital-Clinch Valley, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Jefferson Memorial Hospital Corporation, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - John Randolph Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Johnston Memorial Hospital Inc., 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Johnston-Willis Hospital Inc., 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - King's Daughter's Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Lake Taylor City Hospital, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Lee County Community Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Leigh Memorial Hospital Division Medical Center Hospitals, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Lewis-Gale Hospital Inc., 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Lonesome Pine Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Loudoun Memorial Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Lynchburg General-Marshall Lodge Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Louise Obici Memorial Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Martha Jefferson Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Mary Immaculate Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Mary Washington Hospital Inc., 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Maryview Hospital Corp., 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Mattie Williams Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Medical College of Virginia, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Memorial Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Memorial Hospital of Martinsville, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Montgomery County Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Mount Vernon Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - National Hospital for Orthopedics and Rehabilitation, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Newport News General (Formerly Whittaker Memorial Hospital) 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Norfolk Community Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Norfolk General Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Norfolk Psychiatric Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Northampton-Accomack Memorial, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Northern Virginia Doctor's Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Norton Community Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Page Memorial Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Park Avenue Hospital Inc., 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Peninsula Psychiatric Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Poplar Springs Hospital (Formerly Petersburg Psychiatric Institute), 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Portsmouth General Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Portsmouth Psychiatric Center, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Potomac Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Prince William Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Psychiatric Institute of Richmond, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Pulaski Community Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - R.J. Reynolds-Patrick County, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Radford Community Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Rappahannock General Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Retreat Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Richmond Community Hospital Inc., 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Richmond Eye and Ear Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Richmond Memorial Hospital, 1978-1982 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Richmond Metropolitan Hospital, 1978-1983 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Riverside Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Roanoke Memorial Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Roanoke Valley Psychiatric Center Inc., 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Rockingham Memorial Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Russell County Medical Center, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - St. Albans Psychiatric Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - St. Mary's Hospital Norton, Virginia (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - St. Mary's Hospital Richmond, Virginia (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Sheltering Arms Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Shenandoah County Memorial Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Smyth County Community Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Southampton Memorial Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Southside Community Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Southside Regional Medical Center (Formerly Petersburg General Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Springwood Psychiatric Institute, 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Stonewall Jackson Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Stuart Circle Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Tazewell Community Hospital Inc., 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Tidewater Memorial Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Tidewater Psychiatric Institute, 1980-1983 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Tidewater Psychiatric Institute of Virginia Beach, 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Twin County Community Hospital Inc., 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - University of Virginia Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Baptist Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Virginia Beach General Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Heart Institute, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Walter Reed Memorial Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Warren Memorial Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Waynesboro Community Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Williamsburg Community Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Winchester Memorial Hospital, 1978-1983 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Wise Appalachian Regional Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Wythe County Community Hospital, 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Wytheville Hospital Corporation, 1979-1983 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - CLOSED-Ambulatory Surgical Center of Leigh Memorial Hospital, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - CLOSED-Bristol Memorial Hospital, 1979-1981 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - CLOSED-Burrell Memorial Hospital, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - CLOSED-Elks National Home, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - CLOSED-Gordonsville Community Hospital Inc., 1979-1982 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - CLOSED-Thomas K. McKee Hospital, 1979-1981 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - EXEMPTION-Lynn House of Potomac Valley Inc., (Religious Institution), 1980 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - EXEMPTION-Woodrow Wilson Rehabilitation Center, (State Facility) 1979 (Box 5, Folder 30)